Isabella M. Henry papers, Inclusive: 1931-1981, undated, Bulk: 1943-1949, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Isabella M. Henry papers
Inclusive: 1931-1981, undated, Bulk: 1943-1949, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3157
Henry, Isabella Martin
1 oversize photograph box.
The Isabella M. Henry papers contain correspondence, legal documents, literary productions, and photographs of Isabella M. Henry pertaining to her service in the Women's Army Corps (WAC) and Women's Army Auxiliary Corps (WAAC) during World War II.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Isabella Martin Henry was born in Waco, Texas on 1910 September 27. Isabella was the second oldest daughter of Lawrence Seymour Henry and Anna Sloane Ingram. Her family lived and worked in Waco with her father owning the L.S. Henry Printing and Stationery Company.
Before joining the United States Armed Forces, Henry had an excellent education that prepared her for her military career. Henry attended the Academy of Sacred Heart in Waco, Waco High School, and the College of Industrial Arts in Denton, Texas. Henry later earned a Bachelor's degree from the University of Texas in Austin, briefly attended the University of California at Berkley, and received her Master of Arts in sociology from Texas State College for Women in Denton, Texas.
Isabella Henry had a successful career after the introduction of women into the Armed Forcesduring World War II. Because Henry had no dependents, she was able to enlist in the Women's Army Auxiliary Corps in 1942 August and was inducted into the service on 1942 September 7. She was later appointed to the rank of Third Officer on 1943 January 9. On 1948 December 8, Henry was promoted to First Lieutenant in the Women's Army Corps.
The members of the Women's Army Corps were the first women to serve within the ranks of the United States Army. With this new opportunity for women in World War II, women served a variety of roles both in the United States and overseas. Henry has been noted for her influence on the unit's news publications throughout the United States Continental Army Command.
For her service, Isabella M. Henry received numerous honors. Henry received the certificate of commendation from the Chief of Ordnance for her services that ranged from 1944 August 10-1945 December 2. Henry also won the Army commendation ribbon in 1945 for her work in the Field Service sub office at Frankford Arsenal in Philadelphia as the Assistant in the Redistribution and Disposal Division and Stock Control Division. In addition, she was awarded a Certificate of Achievement from the United States Continental Army Command. After nineteen years of dedicated service, Henry retired from active duty on 1961 January 1. She was a lifetime member of the Women's Army Corps Museum Society.
At the completion of her service, Henry stated that she intended to visit her siblings. Isabella Henry had two sisters, Henrietta and Mary Catherine, and one brother, Lawrence. On 1994 February 20, Isabella passed away and was buried at Holy Cross Cemetery in Waco, Texas.
Scope and Content
The Isabella M. Henry papers consist of materials dating from 1931-1981 and undated materials. The Literary Production series is the largest in the collection. The numerous certificates for various honors as a WAC and WAAC member and her overall military records describe her military career.
Arrangement
The Isabella M. Henry papers were not organized prior to this finding aid, and no prior inventory existed. The collection was dispersed among two folders. Currently, the Isabella M. Henry papers are arranged in four series: I.Correspondence, II. Legal Documents, III. Literary Productions, and IV. Photographic Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3157. Acquired 1995-03-00
Related Resources
Related references
Bellafaire, Judith A. "The Women's Army Corps: A Commemoration of World War II Service." US Army Center Of Military History. Accessed 2012 February 8.
Find a Grave, Inc. "Isabella M. Henry." Memorial #12847774. Databases. Accessed 2012 February 8.
"First Retiring WAC At Post Given Citation." Daily Press, 1960 December 31.
Isabella M. Henry Papers, Accession #3157, Box #1, Folder #1-8, The Texas Collection, Baylor University.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
United States. Army. Women's Army Corps -- History.
Places
United States -- Armed Forces -- Women.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945 -- Women.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genres
Certificates.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Military records.; Photographs.
- Correspondence, 1931-1949, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The Correspondence Series contains general correspondence of which the majority concerns Isabella M. Henry and her military service. Most of the documentation details the specifics of the certificates she received and includes letters of appreciation for her time served.
  - General, 1931-1946 (Box [1062] OVZ, Folder 1)
  - United States Government, 1943-1949, undated (Box [1062] OVZ, Folder 2)
- Legal Documents, 1943-1967; 2
  The Legal Documents Series consists of documentation such as Isabella M. Henry's military history, personal history, military identification card, and general documents.
  - Military Personal Records, 1943-1967 (Box [1062] OVZ, Folder 3)
- Literary Productions, 1943-1981, undated; 3
  The Literary Productions Series contains art, military certificates, membership certificates and news clippings concerning Isabella M. Henry's service in and retirement from the United States military.
  - Art, undated (Box [1062] OVZ, Folder 4)
  - Certificates (1 of 2), 1943-1981 (Box [1062] OVZ, Folder 5)
  - Certificates (2 of 2), 1943-1981 (Box [1062] OVZ, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1960, undated (Box [1062] OVZ, Folder 7)
- Photographic Materials, undated; 4
  The Photographic Materials Series contains undated photographs and a slide of Isabella M. Henry.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - Photographs, undated (Box [1062] OVZ, Folder 8)